Guide to the E. G. Barham Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
E. G. Barham papers
1938-1995
SC0679
Barham, E. G. (Eric George)
8.5 Linear feet
These papers include correspondence (professional and personal), field notes, dive notes, reading notes, class materials, articles, and photographs from deep sea dives and aerial surveys of dolphins.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Eric Barham, a pioneer in biological research from submersible vehicles, earned his Ph.D. at Stanford in 1957; his dissertation was on the ecology of sonic scattering layers in the Monterey Bay area of California. His career included positions at San Diego State, the Naval Electronic Laboratory in San Diego, and the Southwest Fisheries Center.
Description of the Collection
These papers include correspondence (professional and personal), field notes, dive notes, reading notes, class materials, articles, and photographs from deep sea dives and aerial surveys of dolphins.
Access Terms
Barham, E. G. (Eric George); Wible, Joe; Dolphins--Pacific Ocean.; Oceanographic submersibles.; Oceanography--Research.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Correspondence, early retirement, Los Osos Period A-C (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, early retirement, Los Osos Period G-S (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, notes, photographs of deep submersible observations originally intended as book chapters (Box 1, Folder 3-9)
  - 1987 calendar (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Field work – trout, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Notebooks (2) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Calendar 1990, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Logbook 1967 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Porpoise problem water front notes Spring 1973 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Field notes NEL 1959-60 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Field notes NEL 3190, 1963-64 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Notebook – biological data 1958-59 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Notebook – Gorgonian catalogue (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Diving log, 1961-69 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous notebooks (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Field notes – fishing trips 1971-75 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Fishing trips – expenses and notes 1971 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Fishing log, July-August 1971 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Fishing notes (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Class materials, CAL Poly – Coastal Resource Management 1985 (Box 1, Folder 27-29)
  - Correspondence re class (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Coastal Resource Management (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Student chapter – questions (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Student chapter – activities (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Notebook, miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Fishing notes (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Fishing notebooks (2) 1971, 1979-80 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Fishing trip notes 1974 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Fishing trips – miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Group 1: unfiled correspondence re early retirement 1980-81; last letter from Gene Dodge (Box 2)
  - Group 2: manuscript, photos, reprints, etc. re deep submersible research (Box 2)
  - Group 3: old NEWL bulletin board pinups, photos, letters to Gordon Tucker from HMS (Box 2)
  - Dive 113 critical proof of siph. Importance (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Dive 194 results pertaining to sound scattering (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Notes on Bigelow’s Reports on the Scientific Results of the Expedition to the Eastern Tropical Pacific 1911 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Soli, G. “Biological environment as related to the transmission of sound in the sea” 1959 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Halliday, V. “Doppler Structure in Echoes from Schools of Pelagic Fish” (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Charts used for Riverside – Vert. Dist. Symposium June 1965 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Deep Star Program – memorandum and photographs (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Dive 346, fish photographs (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Deep Star dive 159, medusa capture photographs (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Deep Star dives 105-106, photos of cystonec siphs fouled on wire (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Negatives (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Reading notes (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Photographs of neuatophores of siphnophores, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Photographs from dives 1965 and undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Research note card (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, Betty to Eric, March 1966 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, Betty to Eric, April 1966 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, children to Eric 1966 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, Betty to Eric 1967, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, Eric to Betty 1967 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Unidentified photos from correspondence (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, undated and fragments (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1962-63 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1965-66 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1967-68 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, Jim King, 1964-65 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, from Elsie, 1963-65 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, C. E. Moritz, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Klamath River Basin Bull Trout Recovery Plan. Part 1 A Conceptual Framework for Recovery. Draft II for the Crater Lake Meeting March 21-22, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - The Mexican Connection [aerial photos of dolphins??] (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Barham, “Aerial Surveys of Eastern Tropical Pacific Dolphin Populations: History, Methods, Recommendations” (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Distribution – aerial survey (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Assorted reports and papers (Box 3)
  - Taylor, J. “Aircraft Assessment of the Porpoise Population,” with letter (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Notes and map from aerial survey 1974 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Test Report; Porpoise Film Selection Test (Box 3, Folder nf)
  - Aerial survey 1977: aircraft procurement (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Aerial survey 1977: flight plans (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Aerial survey 1977: work shop (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Aerial survey 1977: letters (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Aerial survey 1977: letters (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Aerial survey 1977: phone numbers and addresses (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Aerial survey 1977: memos and correspondence (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Maps (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Assorted reports/papers (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous letter, map, reprint (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Slides “consider using for aerial survey review paper” (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Materials from his work and papers on Tursiops and Grampus; some biographical materials (Box 4)
  - Drafts of several papers (Box 5)
  - Published papers and reports (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous materials (Box 5)
  - Photographs of capture of “medusa” sea creature; of aerial location of dolphins and the airplane used (Box 5)
  - Personal correspondence 1938-45 (Box 5)
  - Oversize film negatives; illustration; calendars (Box 6)
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2004-223
  - Echograms (negatives) from Deepstar dives in San Diego trough, etc., ca. 1968 (Box 1)
  - Pneumatophore measurements done by "Marg"; NEL – ca. 1964-65 (Box 1)